<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="layout.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>

<content>

<h1 class="top">Introduction</h1>

<p>Ratch stands for <u>R</u>uby-based b<u>atch</u> files. Specifically Ratch is a Domain 
Specific Language for writing batch scripts in Ruby. ... Ratch is being used as the 
bases of Reap services, making it much more convient to build project scripts
than plain Ruby provides.</p>

<p>Use Ratch as you would Ruby when writing a script. Instead of the ruby shebang line
use a ratch shebang line.</p>

<pre>
  #!/usr/bin/env ratch
</pre>

<p>For details on all that Ratch provides, see the RDocs.</p>

<p>Ratch is still Beta sofware. The DSL will continue to evolve for the foreseeable future.</p>


<h1>Installation</h1>

<p>Via RubyGems:</p>

<pre>
  $ gem install ratch
</pre>

<p>To install from source you will need <a href="http://setup.rubyforge.org">Ruby Setup</a>.</p>

<pre>
  $ tar -xzf ratch-x.y.z.tar.gz
  $ cd ratch-x.y.z
  $ setup.rb all
</pre>

<p>Microsoft Windows users, you'll have to use '@ruby task/setup@' instead.</p>


<h1>Development</h1>

<p>You can use gitweb to browse the 'ratch' repository.</p>

<p>To pull the 'ratch' repository anonymously, use:</p>

<pre>
  git clone git://rubyforge.org/ratch.git
</pre>  

<p>Developers: You can push to the 'ratch' repository using:</p>

<pre>
  gitosis@rubyforge.org:ratch.git
</pre>    

<h1>Copying</h1>

<p>Ratch -- Ruby-based Batch Files</p>

<p>Copyright &#x00A9; 2007 TigerOps (Sponsered by &#x3c8;&#x3c4; Corp.)</p>

<p>This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program.  If not, see 
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</a>.</p>

</content>
